coffee, the microbiome, and kissing.
What do these three things have in
common? Dr. Tim Spectre. Now, Dr.
Spectre is a medical doctor, a professor
in epidemiology, and a founder of a
health company called Zoey. Now, in this
episode of The Centrifuge, where we spin
out the fiction from the fact by
providing scientific references for or
against claims made on health podcasts,
we'll be getting into a number of
topics. the microbiome and the impact of
coffee, kissing, and your microbiome.
How scandalous microbiome diversity and
your health. Now, as usual, summaries at
the end, skippable timestamps for your
convenience, and let's spin it.
>> How can you explain that to someone that
doesn't know much about the gut?
>> When I'm talking about your gut, I'm
talking about gut microbes. And there
are 40 to 100 trillion of these guys in
your mainly in your large intestine that
are
many pharmacies. And
there we have thousands of different
species, all of which highly selected to
eat only certain foods. There's one that
only likes coffee, for example, called
Lorenabacta.
>> A bug that only likes coffee in my
belly. It's
>> just waiting for you to drink coffee.
>> And when I drink coffee, what happens?
it uh has a party, has sex, has babies,
multiplies, and then produces certain
chemicals in response by breaking down
that coffee into other ingredients which
might then help your immune system and
um in some way explain why coffee is
good for your heart.
>> So the first claim is that our
intestinal microbiome contains a microbe
called loeninoactctor that feeds on
coffee and is beneficial for our heart
health. Now Dr. Spectre not only has a
leg to stand on, but likely multiple. If
he were a squid, he'd have many. And
that's primarily because he published a
huge study on this very topic along with
many other researchers. Now, in said
study, they assessed the relationship
between coffee consumption and this very
lossactor bacterium. We can see that
here. We have many different groups of
people assessed, five different samples
of thousands of people from all over the
globe, including some groups data
collected by the very same Zoey company
that Dr. Spectre is currently part of.
Then we have three different levels of
consumption of coffee. If the blobs of
data move up, that means that there's
more of this bacterium in that amount of
coffee consumption. The FC at the top is
fold change. So quite massive
differences between the coffee
consumption across groups of people.
Those who consume some coffee have more
of this bacterium. And sometimes
consuming even more coffee led to more
of this bacterium. But to be clear, this
is a simple association. So we don't
actually know if this is causal, as in
coffee is causing this bacterium to
grow. Fortunately, this very same study
did some simple experiments where they
applied coffee to this lossactor as well
as some other bacterium and they only
reliably raise concentrations of this
bacterium and not others. This tells us
definitively that coffee causes this
bacterium to grow. In terms of what is
moderate and high consumption, we're
talking about less than three cups per
day for moderate and more than three
cups per day for high. So, Dr. Spectre
is fully precise in his description.
Coffee not only associates with grace
greater loss in actor presence, but
causes it to grow. Now, that's all well
and good, but who cares if this
bacterium isn't linked to better health?
So, Dr. perspective points out that the
relationship to heart health and
admittedly the research is is not as
clear-cut as the previous study that we
just went over, but it does lean in the
direction of an association for lower
gut loss and ovacular presence being
linked to unstable chest pain and
coronary artery disease. Now these kinds
of studies are not strong evidence but
considering that this assessment and the
fact that coffee tends to be a net
benefit for the heart we can at least
lean in the direction of a of that claim
being correct. So the second claim loss
of aobacttor presence is linked to
better heart health is leaning true
though not foolproof. Now kissing what
does that have to do with health and the
microbiome? So if I stop eating a
particular food like coffee, if I stop
having coffee, will that bug die?
>> It probably goes down to very low levels
because actually what's interesting is
even if you stop drinking coffee, you're
surrounded by coffee drinkers.
And they they're droplets of saliva and
kisses and uh greetings mean that you'll
be getting uh some of that. either those
bugs themselves or you'll be getting um
some bits of coffee in the air, a coffee
aroma.
>> Okay. So, the bugs go up and down in
population.
>> Yes. So, even in non- coffee drinkers,
we do see tiny amounts of this uh this
Lorsonacta. So, the claim here is to
make out with more people.
Okay, maybe I'm misinterpreting, but we
could go with that. Right. Right.
Okay. The real claim is that even non-
coffee drinkers have some of these
coffee specific beneficial bacteria
simply because they're around people who
drink coffee. And this isn't restrictive
to just coffee, but all kinds of foods.
Now, I want to pause here and point out
that A, how weird is that? And B, how
cool is that? Being around others can
change our microbiome simply because we
exist around others. So we'll check this
in two ways. One directly and two we can
actually look back at this initial huge
study on coffee. The direct measure or
the direct assessment I should say is a
study where researchers had couples give
microbiome samples then one person
consumed probiotic yogurt. So, it
contained bacteria. And then they made
out for 10 seconds. And then the non-
yogurt eating partner had their
microbiome checked. And sure enough,
there was a micro transfer. However,
this seems almost obvious. I mean, swap
and spit with your significant other.
Did I ruin the romance? Uh, would carry
a microbiome crossover when we're
assessing it at the mouth. But what
about the gut? We also see similar
results associatively when people live
together and when they don't. People who
live together tend to have more diverse
microbiomes shown here as a common
assessment called a Shannon index. Those
who cohabitate versus those who don't
after diet is accounted for still tend
to have greater gut microbiome
diversity. This isn't definitive proof,
but there are other studies that look at
other microbiomes and show similar
trends. Now, in addition to that, it's
also true that we see signals of
maintaining a microbiome by simply being
around others that consume the micro
food
food that we don't consume. If we return
to this study and check out the results
across the United States only, you'll
see the different coffee consuming
groups on the bottom and the prevalence
of the same bacterium that we've been
focused on. Now the more red the more of
this bacterium is present based on the
amount of coffee consumed. But that's
old news. We already know that coffee
directly affects this lossbacttor
bacterium. But check out the far left
condition. That's people who never
consume coffee. And yes, the graph is
very much not red. But the scale in red
indicates close to 100% prevalence. And
the bottom of the scale isn't 0%, it's
85% which is still incredibly high. So
even though these people don't consume
coffee, the vast majority still have
this bacterium to some degree. Now, is
that necessarily because of this shared
microbiome between people? Not
necessarily. We've been focused on
coffee, but that doesn't mean that other
things can't also stimulate this
bacterium. So, could tea stimulate it?
Definitely. Could something else?
Definitely. So, this isn't foolproof
evidence, but in combination, it nudges
that possibility. The point here is that
yes, even independent of diet, we
experience changes to our microbiome, if
that's through intimate contact or
otherwise. Yet, the real question that's
on your mind is most definitely, do you
make out or not? Obviously, the answer
is yes. But you don't need a microbiome
related reason for that justification,
do you?
>> I think it's important to imagine your
It's a bit like having a rare animal.
You know, you've got to feed in your
zoo. You don't want to give them all the
same food. You've got to give them this
diversity so that all the rare animals
can get out there. And we know that the
more good bugs you've got,
the better your immune system, the more
you dampen inflammation, the more you
can prevent all these problems that
we're we're seeing. So our our aim is to
build up the good bugs. And the more you
build them up, they squash out the bad
bugs, the ones that like eating the
burgers and the the the bad food and the
and the terrible quality fats and the
artificial substances. So you're
squashing them out by starving them and
you do that by feeding them properly. So
that's the that's the concept if that
makes sense.
>> The claim here is that we need to give
our gut microbiome the specific foods
that allow the good microbes an
advantage to survive and the bad
microbes get starved out. And that
scenario allows the microbiome to reduce
our risk of disease and inflammation.
Now I'd like to get into that and we
will. But if you're looking for more on
different types of coffee and their
impact on our microbiome or a specific
molecule in certain coffees that
stimulates the microbiome or how our
siblings impact our microbiome and more,
then check out the full analysis of the
one that you're currently watching. It's
included in my Physionic Insider
membership and it even comes with a full
article, a one paragraph summary of the
most important points. And if you're
keen, all of these perks like live
sessions, which I'm actually having one
soon. So, if you're free on the weekend,
consider joining. Anyway, link to join
the insiders is in the is
is in the description box. I hope to see
you there. Unfortunately, there's no
specificity here on what's a good and
bad micro. So, I'll have to use a
liberal take and look at the microbiome
diversity where studies do indicate that
reduced microbiome diversity which comes
partly from consuming less varied foods
is linked to worse metabolic health from
more body fat to greater insulin
resistance than people with greater
microbiome diversity. Now, to be fair
here, it should be pointed out that we
can't necessarily attribute the cause of
this difference to the microbiome, just
that it's correlated. For that, pretty
complex intervention studies have to be
used, looking at rich microbiota and
transplanting them in people with
obesity and insulin resistance and then
measuring if just the changing of the
gut microbiome can offer benefit. It
does. This is a bit of a difficult claim
to completely substantiate, but the data
certainly leans in the direction of it
being true. Typically, more diverse
microbiomes are related to better health
status. So, all in all, Dr. Spectre is
pretty spot-on with all of his points. I
suppose this shouldn't really be much of
a surprise considering his strong
research background. As for the final
points, first coffee does cause loss of
bacterium to grow and this is generally
seen as a good thing as it's tentatively
linked to better heart health. Our
microbiome can shift independent of our
diet and is influenced by our romantic
partners becoming more similar. And
generally, more diverse microbiome
tracks with better overall health. And
finally, if you're looking for more
centerfuge episodes, check this one out
right here. Also, give your romantic
partner a smooch and blame it on wanting
a more similar microbiome. How romantic.
Thanks for watching. Catch you in the
next one. See you.